Previously on Gotham...
Ooh...
(men shouting)
What you call sanity...
Hey!
...is just a prison
in your mind.
(laughing)
Bang.
(laughter)
Wake up!
(grunting)
You're the one who's
been following us.
Do you know her?
That's my mom.
Isabella's death
has altered things,
and I can't continue.
No! Ed, I will not
let you leave.
I don't want to kill him.
I want to destroy him.
GORDON: Tetch infected him
that night in the hospital.
Swear that you'll
bring him in alive.
I swear.
THOMPKINS:
After the wedding,
Mario and I are leaving Gotham.
I'll never see you again.
Lee, you cannot marry him.
Get the hell out of here!
(screams)
"And the end will come
when he hands over
"the kingdom to God,
the Father,
"after he has destroyed
all dominion.
"The last enemy
to be destroyed is death."
In nomine Patris
et Filii tu y Santos.
Amen.
MOURNERS:
BULLOCK:
Jim.
What the hell
are you doing here?
If Falcone sees you,
God only knows what he'll do.
I had to do it, Harv.
He was infected.
He would've killed her.
It was a legit kill.
That's the law.
This is family.
The man's burying his son.
Lee's burying a husband.
I wanted to...
(exhales)
I don't know.
To what?
Say sorry?
Talk about the past?
This isn't the time
or the place. Come on.
(mourners sobbing)
(buttons beeping)
(line ringing)
(on phone):
This is Edward.
Leave a message.
Or don't.
Doesn't really matter.
(voice mail beeps)
Hey! Ooh.
What?
Mayor, the press have assembled
in the conference room.
They are requesting
your presence.
The press? Why?
The latest figures are in.
Fine.
Let the vultures have at me.
(indistinct chatter)
MAN:
Hey, there he is.
(applause, clamoring)
They're through the
roof across the board.
Yeah, jobs are up,
market's up.
Crime way, way down.
You did it.
Enjoy the moment,
sir.
Excuse me. Coming through.
Excuse me.
Praise well deserved,
Mr. Mayor.
I really think we need
to cash in on this good news
immediately.
You are a clever fellow,
Tarquin, but...
I wish Ed were here.
TARQUIN:
My sole job as deputy chief
of staff is to serve you
with the exact same
zeal and smarts
as Mr. Nygma would.
Thank you all so much
for coming.
Thanks, everyone.
Bob, great to see you.
Bill, take care.
(indistinct chatter)
Margaret Hearst.
Know her?
Of course.
When I saw these numbers come
in, I thought who better
to help us capitalize on this
than Margaret Hearst?
The whole city-- no, the whole
country-- watches her show.
She can take you
to a whole new level.
Solidify your legacy
on a national scale.
"National scale"?
She's in my office,
and she is dying
to meet you.
Turn her down now,
she won't come back,
like... ever.
What do you say?
How's my hair?
(clanging nearby)
(glugging)
Hope you don't mind.
I helped myself.
What do you want?
I'm here
as a messenger.
Okay, I'm listening.
You messed up, Jim.
Killed the don's son.
He's beside himself.
I've never seen him
like this before.
I want to speak to him.
Oh, no,
we're way past that.
It's only a matter of time
before he gives the nod to...
(clucks tongue)
...put a bullet
in your head.
You could try.
I don't... try.
And I never stop.
You won't see me coming.
And you won't
feel a thing.
If we don't get a chance
to talk before then,
it's been really
nice knowing you.
You're a good egg.
Also...
nice shot on Mario.
I never liked him.
♪ ♪
Nice place.
What's with the raggedy clothes?
Why are you back?
To see you,
of course.
(quietly scoffs)
Why now?
Why wait 11 years
to see me?
That's right.
11 years.
You didn't even
check up on me.
What can I say?
I'm sorry,
and you have no idea
how many times
I thought of you.
How many times, Mom?
I had to leave.
I had no choice.
You know that orphanage
I left you at?
It's the same one I was
left at by who knows who.
St. Maria's.
It's where I got my name.
I grew up there
and on the streets.
It was on the streets
that I had you.
Who's my father?
You're not dating that kid,
are you?
(sighs)
You should go.
Wait, I me--
I was a dumb kid, okay?
I got in trouble with the law.
I had to leave or they were
gonna take me to prison.
I had to run
and run fast.
And you can't run fast
with a five-year-old.
Not just a five-year-old.
Your five-year-old.
Your daughter.
That was a bad call.
Okay?
I just wanted to come here,
and tell you that I love you.
And I'm sorry.
All righty then.
This has been
so fun.
Bye.
Selina.
Good-bye.
(sighs)
Mayor, this...
is Ms. Hearst.
Perhaps you've
truly found
your calling in office,
Mr. Cobblepot.
Or perhaps...
you just know how to show people
only what they want to see.
Hmm?
Either way, I plan
to get inside your head
and share what I find
with the citizens
of Gotham.
Does that deter you?
Please.
Then I think
the exclusive interview
should happen
here at city hall
this Friday, live.
Actually, I would prefer
to do it at home and...
Uh, uh, uh, uh, uh.
This Friday
or not at all.
I'll be honest with
you, Mr. Mayor.
I'm not a fan.
I shan't be
holding back.
My audience expects the truth
and I give it to them.
The truth is in my numbers,
Ms. Hearst.
Then Friday it is.
Gotham will see their mayor...
as he truly is.
Dig deep.
I have nothing to hide.
LUCIUS:
Melanie Blake.
Found wandering
the train tracks
late last night
in a state of undress.
She collapsed soon after,
and died in the ambulance
of coronary failure.
At some point prior to her
appearance on the tracks,
somebody applied a strong
electrical current to her.
Considering the extent
of the burns,
I'm guessing literally
thousands of volts
were passed
through this poor girl.
Torture?
Perhaps.
She say anything before she die?
No.
GORDON:
She was...
stabbed as well?
Melanie was stabbed three
days ago by her boyfriend.
She was pronounced dead
in the ambulance.
Wait, w-what?
Two days ago,
this girl was taken
to the morgue,
dead.
BULLOCK:
And yet last night,
she's walking down the train
tracks after getting zapped
with 10,000 volts
in her noggin?
Doesn't anyone die
in Gotham anymore?
Is it possible she
wasn't actually dead,
and just walked
out of the morgue?
These days I no longer
say impossible.
Unlikely.
The morgue.
It's not a morgue, it's a motel.
Harvey!
As acting captain,
I demand that you arrest
Detective Gordon
for the murder of my husband.
Lee...
please.
Please?
Please...
what?!
You didn't have
to kill him.
Dr. Thompkins,
if I may,
your husband
took a drug that--
Nathaniel Barnes was infected
with the same virus.
He's alive.
Jim spared his life.
And yet he gunned down Mario
on his wedding day.
You're the real virus, Jim.
You seep into people's lives
until you destroy them.
You haven't heard
the end of this.
(thunder crashing)
(fire crackling)
(glass shatters)
(gasps)
(thunder rumbling)
(creaking)
(gasping)
(glass shatters)
Father?
Help me.
My God.
(panting)
Of course. How?
He's not to be trusted.
Who?
(violent thunderclap)
(pounding on door)
Sorry to bother you
so late, Mr. Mayor.
Yes. What is it?
Someone broke into
the cemetery and dug up
your father's remains.
(thunder rolls)
GCPD.
You the night manager
here, Mister, uh...
Pollard?
Dwight, please, that's correct.
Something wrong?
Only if you call dead people
walking out of here wrong.
What?
Melanie Blake.
She would have been
here two days ago.
Yeah.
Stabbing victim.
Drawer 12.
(rollers squeaking)
That's not right.
That's because she's
on the M.E.'s slab,
dead, again.
What?
You have any security
cameras here? Guards?
No, we don't need them.
Nothing ever happens down here.
(loud bang)
Sorry.
BULLOCK:
Hey.
You jumpy, Jim?
Uh, we're all good.
You got something
you want to share?
No.
Let's stick around.
See where this
Dwight takes us.
BRUCE:
I don't get it.
Why is it so important
to the Court of Owls?
It's just an ornament.
I don't know.
Men died protecting it.
So we hide it,
hold onto it for leverage
in case they come for us again.
Perhaps in the cave.
(knocking)
Ms. Kyle.
What a surprise.
For what do we owe
this pleasure?
I was just leaving this
here for Selina.
Oh.
Uh... come in.
Please stay.
We've been meaning to thank you
in person for the other night.
I can't.
I have a train to catch.
Please just see
that she gets this.
ALFRED:
Would you mind if I asked
what's in the box?
Some things I kept from
my time here in Gotham.
It's not something you'd like
to give to Selina yourself?
I tried reaching
out to her.
She's too angry.
Not that I can blame her.
Please, just...
see that she gets this.
BRUCE:
Ms. Kyle?
Take it from someone who misses
his family very much.
Please don't leave just yet.
I know where she is.
Let me talk to her.
Okay, thanks.
This keeps getting
better and better.
Guess where Dwight Pollard
worked before the morgue.
Indian Hill.
How'd you know?
Where else in Gotham
do the dead
get brought back to life?
The cops came by, idiot.
How'd she get out?
Never mind.
I have to get to the venue.
I'll come by after.
Should we grab him now?
No, I want to see
where he's going.
THOMPKINS:
The autopsy showed that
Mario did have the virus.
Mario was my son.
Whether he was sick or not
is of no concern to me.
Gordon took his life.
What are you gonna do?
I cared for Jim Gordon.
In some ways, he was
more like my son than Mario.
His life is mine to take.
That's the natural law.
Blood for blood.
I hate him.
God, I hate him.
Everything bad
that's happened in my life
has happened because of him.
If Gordon dies,
it's a weight we'll
both have to carry.
I'm used to such burdens.
You're not.
He'll die by my hand,
not yours.
But this is something
you'll need to live with.
Can you?
(crying quietly)
(door creaks)
What is that?
Your mother brought
it to my house.
Just leave it there.
I'll get it later.
Selina... I
know how long
you've waited to
see your mother.
I can't imagine all
you must be feeling.
She left me here, Bruce.
Alone.
You're right.
It's hard to forgive.
It may be the
hardest thing
any of us have
to do in this life.
But she's reaching out.
And it may be your only
chance to reach back.
(scoffs)
She's a crook.
Can't you see that?
She's still your mother.
Push her away now and you
may never see her again.
(footsteps approaching)
(sobbing softly)
(siren wailing)
(indistinct chatter)
♪ ♪
BULLOCK:
Okay.
Weird...
But not illegal.
(feedback echoes)
(cheers and applause)
Okay.
Weirder.
The people of this city
are slaves.
Mm-hmm. See,
they get up every day
and go to work
so they can pay their taxes,
their mortgages.
See, they believe
what the papers tell them.
They fear what
the politicians feed them.
See, they are mentally shackled,
and yet,
they do nothing about it!
(cheering, applause)
Yeah! Nothing!
But there was someone
who understood.
Someone who spoke out,
who stood up,
to the jailers, puppets.
A man with no fear.
♪ ♪
JEROME:
Hello, Gotham City!
We're the Maniax.
And I'm Jerome,
the shot caller
of our little gang.
We're here to spread the message
of wisdom and hope.
(cackles)
(man groaning on video)
(gunshot)
Some people have no manners.
(laughter)
You're all
prisoners.
ALL:
What you call sanity,
it's just a prison in your minds
that stops you from seeing
you're just tiny little cogs
in a giant, absurd machine,
Wake up!
Oh!
(laughter)
Time to go.
(sirens wailing)
But don't worry.
We'll be back very soon.
Hang onto your hats, folks.
ALL: 'Cause you ain't seen
nothing yet!
(laughter)
(cheering, applause)
All right!
Show's over!
Time to go home.
BULLOCK:
GCPD!
(gunshot)
(crowd shouting, clamoring)
Let's go!
(laughter)
(woman screams)
(Jerome laughing)
You see Dwight?
He was probably the last one
to jump on the clown car.
Bringing back the dead
is something we need to, uh...
Oh, no...
What?
(gunshots)
Back!
(grunts)
Who the hell's that?
It's Victor Zsasz.
Falcone put out a hit on me.
Oh!
Would've been nice if
you told me that earlier!
He's only after me.
Zsasz is very professional
in that way.
(gunshots continue)
Trapped behind here,
we're sitting ducks.
I need to draw their fire.
Find me later.
Wait, Jim. Don't!
Damn it.
(indistinct chatter)
Everyone out!
It's not safe.
Hey, who is this guy?
What are you deaf?
Get out of here!
(gunfire)
(shouting, clamoring)
(panicked chatter)
It's inevitability, Jim.
Embrace it.
You've had a good run.
You should know that.
♪ ♪
(thunder rolling)
WOMAN (echoing):
♪ Happy birthday to you ♪
Who's there?
(panting)
(door slams)
Father?
WOMAN (echoing):
♪ Happy birthday ♪
♪ To you ♪
Father.
How can I help you?
What can I do?
Find me, my son.
I cannot rest
until I lay underground
once more.
He cannot
be trusted!
Who?
Isabella is over
on the other side with us.
Whispering tales of murder.
Dark plots are in
motion, my son.
Don't trust him!
Who?
The birthday boy.
(thuds)
(alarm sounding)
You want to know
about your husband.
Was he a diseased maniac?
Would he have
killed you?
Well, I can
tell you this.
I've never felt
better in my life.
Clearer, stronger.
More focused.
Even now,
I can feel it
coursing through my veins.
Restoring my body.
So, Mario could've lived
a normal life with it.
Would've given us time
to find a cure.
Jim didn't have to kill him.
Cure?
This virus isn't the disease.
It's the antidote.
It's the best thing
that's ever happened to me.
I don't need a cure.
The murderers,
thieves, rapists.
(laughs)
James Gordon is one of them.
When I get out of here--
and trust me, I will--
he'll be the first
that I judge.
He and all the other human
garbage that plague this city.
All will be tried,
convicted and executed!
I will purge Gotham,
and the innocents will thank me!
Their savior!
Their executioner.
I know, and the
best part is,
that fake painting is still
hanging in the gallery.
(laughter)
Perhaps we might be able
to talk about something
other than your previous
illicit exploits, Ms. Kyle.
Oh, I'm sorry, Alfred.
This was a great meal.
You're quite the chef.
Thank you very much, miss.
SELINA: He's a catch,
this one.
Got a stiff right hand, too.
Easy mark, though.
(Maria laughs)
Thank you...
very much, cheeky monkey.
Oh, you poor thing.
Come here.
(giggles)
ALFRED: Oh...
(chuckles)
I see what you mean, though.
(Selina chuckles)
ALFRED: Oh, well, that's just...
Just hilarious. You know...
Really. Thank you.
Thank you very much...
Oh, I guess
I better go.
It's late. Stay.
Alfred will drive you to
your hotel in the morning.
(sighs)
You're very kind.
(thunder rolls)
(distant car horns honking)
Mr. Mayor?
S--
Unless you are bringing
strong coffee,
or you have
information
on my father's stolen remains...
...go away.
Yeah, but--
CROWD:
♪ Happy birthday to you ♪
♪ Happy birthday
to you ♪
♪ Happy birthday, dear Tarquin ♪
The birthday boy.
(panting)
(applause in distance)
♪ ♪
(gasps)
(rapid inhaling, exhaling)
Your Honor.
Can I help you?
Why?
Why would you do such a thing?
What are you talking about?
What is that?
You are a sick man!
What are you plotting?
What's the angle?
Who are you in on this with?
I-I have no idea.
Look, you're exhausted.
Y-You haven't slept in days...
(grunts)
You barely...
(yells)
(growls)
(knocking on door)
WOMAN:
Mr. Stemmel?
The TV crew is ready.
It's time for
the interview.
Have you seen
the mayor?
♪ ♪
Carmine... call it off.
Why?
I saw Barnes.
The virus has
completely taken over.
He's insane.
What makes you want
to save Gordon?
Please, just call it off.
You said
you hated him.
That wasn't true, was it?
Call it off now!
You talk of hate
and revenge,
but that's only to mask
what really scares you.
You still love James Gordon.
Where is he?
We're minutes away.
They're looking for him.
Well, look harder.
MAN:
Here he is!
Sorry I'm late.
Mayor stuff.
(chuckles)
(indistinct chatter)
Mr. Mayor, this is a pin...
I hope you're ready,
Mr. Mayor.
The world is watching.
MAN:
And we're live in three,
two...
Mayor Cobblepot,
as Gotham is enjoying
an historic spike
in job growth and prosperity,
it is also going through
one of the safest periods
in its history.
And I'm sure
everyone is wondering,
"How did he do it?"
Uh...
Well...
BULLOCK:
Whoa, hey!
Hello to you, too.
You didn't think
you'd get rid of me
that easily, did you?
I thought we might
need something
with a bit more bite.
So, why didn't you
tell me about Zsasz?
It's my business.
Yeah?
Not yours.
That's a bit ridiculous,
seeing as how
I'm standing next to you
most of the time.
(machine gun fire)
What's up?
Drop it, Jim.
It's your time
to die today.
Not his.
Don't listen to him, Jim.
Shoot him now!
Relax, Zsasz.
Job's cancelled.
You can go home.
Okay, boss.
I'm sorry.
If it was up to me,
you'd be dead.
Whew!
So from humble errand boy
to kitchen worker
to the so-called
"King of Gotham,"
it is said that many died
so you could rise.
Oh...
An exaggeration.
People love to invent scandal.
But it was murder
that sent you to Arkham,
a prison for
the criminally insane.
I rescued the city
from the madman,
Theo Galavan.
Some call it murder.
Others a public service.
And after your
controversial release
from prison,
you met your father,
Elijah Van Dahl.
A man whose identity
your mother kept
from you.
Oh, my God.
Yes, it must have been
very upsetting.
What? Yes.
He also died under
suspicious circumstances.
His wife and step-children
disappearing soon after.
I-I have to go.
Why? Is it because there's
substance to the rumors
that you had them killed
to inherit your father's wealth?
Fa-Father, Father wait!
(woman screams)
Are you feeling well,
Mr. Mayor?
I'm fine.
I-I'm great.
Why would I not be fine?
The people of Gotham,
and America,
want to know the truth.
To hell with the people!
(all gasp)
(laughter)
(indistinct muttering)
Father, wait!
Father?
(gasps, panting)
No! No!
(gasping)
A very good job.
Ah.
He bought it?
Hook, line and sinker.
Ah, voice wasn't quite
right, but, uh, you know...
(slow clapping nearby)
Bravo, boys.
Penguin lost his mind
on national TV,
just like you said
he would.
It's all about
the power of suggestion.
And whispering
in the right ears.
Do what I say, and you'll be
the next chief of staff.
Tell him,
"I'm still grieving."
Margaret Hearse is in
your office waiting for you.
And remember to say
exactly what I told you
about his father.
(thunder rolls)
TABITHA:
Why don't you just leave these
bodies for the cops?
Have him arrested.
That's too easy,
Tabitha.
I want this to be a slow...
painful death.
One of a thousand deep cuts.
First we take away his mind...
That's the part I like.
We destroy his empire
and take it for ourselves.
And then, when this bird is
broken and alone,
we do the humane thing
and put him out of his misery.
Mm.
(laughs)
(laughter)
If there's anything
I can do for you, Ms. Kyle,
please don't...
hesitate to ask.
Wait here.
What's wrong?
Just do it.
(door creaks)
COLE:
Did you think
I wouldn't find you?
MARIA:
I was headed back tomorrow.
COLE:
My money, where is it?
100 grand.
MARIA:
I don't have your money.
COLE:
What do I have to do,
beat it out of you?
Leave her alone!
I told you to stay outside!
Who's this?
Nobody.
We can get you
the money.
Is that so?
Who from?
The guy that dropped you
off in the Rolls Royce?
One of you talk.
Who's the rich guy?
Mom...
Leave her alone.
Well, well.
I hope she know what
a lying cheat you are, Maria.
Bruce will give you the money.
He's a good friend of mine.
Would you relax?
Bruce Wayne?
(pistol dry-clicks)
Well, now,
that changes everything.
Why settle
for a hundred?
Perhaps I'll pay him
a visit, tell him
all about you.
(door shuts)
Who was that?
That was my past
coming back to punish me.
Was he the reason
you left Gotham before?
It's complicated.
We have to warn your friends.
Cole is not someone
they should mess with.
(sighs)
Good job, Mom.
Were you followed?
No, no thanks to you.
How did the girl escape?
You led the cops right to me.
I turned my head
for a minute.
She must have
stumbled out.
But this proves that
your designs work.
She came back to life.
But not for long.
The current's still too strong.
Her body couldn't take it.
We have to move quickly.
Gather the others.
It's time to get him.
♪ ♪
(rat squeaking)